# Alex Mariakakis

Postdoctoral Researcher 185 Stevens Way, Seattle, WA 98195 January 27, 2020 atm15@cs.washington.edu https://atm15.github.io/

# Summary

My dissertation work focused on the application of machine learning and computer vision on smartphone sensor data to create mobile apps that improve access to health screening and safety tools. My current research explores how such tools can be made useful for ordinary people. This includes adding real-time guidance to testing procedures, leveraging passive sensing to improve the test results, and helping developers ensure their tests will be well-received.

# **Education**

# University of Washington and Sage Bionetworks (Seattle, WA)

Sept 2019-present

Post-Doctorate

Advisors: Dr. Anind Dey and Dr. Larsson Omberg

# University of Washington (Seattle, WA)

Sept 2015–June 2019

Computer Science and Engineering PhD

Advisors: Dr. Shwetak Patel and Dr. Jacob Wobbrock

#### University of Washington (Seattle, WA)

Sept 2013–June 2015

Computer Science and Engineering MS

Advisors: Dr. Shwetak Patel and Dr. Jacob Wobbrock

#### **Duke University** (Durham, NC)

Aug 2009–June 2013

Fall 2018

Electrical and Computer Engineering BSE, Computer Science BS

Gaetano Borriello Outstanding Student Award for UbiComp

Advisor: Dr. Romit Roy Choudhury

## Awards, Grants, and Honors

#### University of Washington

Gaetano Borrieno Gattianania Stadent riwara for Corcomp	1 411 2010
Qualcomm Innovation Fellowship	Fall 2015
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship	Fall 2014
Duke University	
Graduation Cum Laude	Spring 2013
Graduation with Departmental Distinction	Spring 2013

Graduation with Departmental Distinction	Spring 2013
Tau Beta Pi	Spring 2013
Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award (ECE)	Spring 2012
Pratt Research Fellowship	. Fall 2012

# **Peer-Reviewed Publications**

[1] Xuhai, X., Shi, H., Yi, X., Liu, W., Yan, Y., Shi, Y., Mariakakis, A., Mankoff, J., Dey, A. K., "EarBuddy: Enabling On-Face Interaction via Wireless Earbuds". In: To appear in Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. CHI '20. 2020.

- [2] Li, H., Whitmire, E., **Mariakakis, A.**, Chan, V., Sample, A., Patel, S., "IDCam: Precise Item Identification for AR-Enhanced Object Interactions". In: 2019 IEEE International Conference on RFID (RFID) (2019). DOI: 10.1109/RFID.2019.8719279. URL: https://doi.org/10.1109/RFID.2019.8719279.
- [3] Mariakakis, A., Wang, E., Patel, S., Goel, M., "Challenges in Realizing Smartphone-Based Health Sensing". In: *IEEE Pervasive Computing* 18.2 (Apr. 2019), pp. 76–84. ISSN: 1536-1268. DOI: 10.1109/MPRV.2019.2907007. URL: https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8794692/.
- [4] McGrath, L. B., Eaton, J. C., Law, A., Mariakakis, A., Patel, S., Levitt, M. R., "Mobile Digital Pupillometry for Rapid Triage of Patients With Severe Traumatic Brain Injury". In: Neurosurgery 66.Supplement\_1 (2019), nyz310\_844. DOI: 10.1093/neuros/nyz310\_844. URL: https://doi.org/10.1093/neuros/nyz310\_844.
- [5] Mariakakis, A., Parsi, S., Patel, S. N., Wobbrock, J. O., "Drunk User Interfaces: Determining Blood Alcohol Level Through Everyday Smartphone Tasks". In: *Proceedings of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. CHI '18. Montreal QC, Canada: ACM, 2018, 234:1–234:13. ISBN: 978-1-4503-5620-6. DOI: 10.1145/3173574.3173808. URL: http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/3173574.3173808.
- [6] Mariakakis, A., Banks, M. A., Phillipi, L., Yu, L., Taylor, J., Patel, S. N., "BiliScreen: Smartphone-based Scleral Jaundice Monitoring for Liver and Pancreatic Disorders". In: Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies 1.2 (2017), p. 20. DOI: 10.1145/3131896.
  URL: http://doi.org/10.1145/3131896.
- [7] Mariakakis, A., Baudin, J., Whitmire, E., Mehta, V., Banks, M. A., Law, A., McGrath, L., Patel, S. N., "PupilScreen: Using Smartphones to Assess Traumatic Brain Injury". In: *Proceedings of the 2017 ACM Interactive, Mobile, Wearable, Ubiquitous Technologies* 1.3 (2017), p. 81. DOI: 10.1145/3131896. URL: http://doi.org/10.1145/3131896.
- [8] Mariakakis, A., Patel, S., "Ocular Symptom Detection using Smartphones". In: Proceedings of the 2016 ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing: Adjunct. ACM. 2016, pp. 435–440. DOI: 10.1145/2968219.2971354. URL: http://doi.org/10.1145/2968219.2971354.
- [9] Mariakakis, A., Srinivasan, V., Rachuri, K., Mukherji, A., "WatchUDrive: Differentiating Drivers and Passengers using Smartwatches". In: 2016 IEEE International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communication Workshops (PerCom Workshops). IEEE. 2016, pp. 1–4. DOI: 10.1109/PERCOMW.2016.7457171. URL: http://doi.org/10.1109/PERCOMW.2016.7457171.
- [10] Mariakakis, A., Wang, E., Patel, S. N., Wen, J. C., "A Smartphone-based System for Assessing Intraocular Pressure". In: Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBC), 2016 IEEE 38th Annual International Conference of the. IEEE. 2016, pp. 4353–4356. DOI: 10.1109/EMBC.2016.7591691. URL: http://doi.org/10.1109/EMBC.2016.7591691.
- [11] Goel, M., Whitmire, E., Mariakakis, A., Saponas, T. S., Joshi, N., Morris, D., Guenter, B., Gavriliu, M., Borriello, G., Patel, S. N., "HyperCam: Hyperspectral Imaging for Ubiquitous Computing Applications". In: Proceedings of the 2015 ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing. ACM. 2015, pp. 145–156. DOI: 10.1145/2750858.2804282. URL: http://doi.org/10.1145/2750858.2804282.
- [12] Mariakakis, A., Goel, M., Aumi, M. T. I., Patel, S. N., Wobbrock, J. O., "SwitchBack: Using Focus and Saccade Tracking to Guide Users' Attention for Mobile Task Resumption". In: *Proceedings of the 33rd Annual ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. ACM. 2015, pp. 2953–2962. DOI: 10.1145/2702123.2702539. URL: http://doi.org/10.1145/2702123.2702539.

- [13] Wang, E. J., Lee, T.-J., Mariakakis, A., Goel, M., Gupta, S., Patel, S. N., "Magnifisense: Inferring Device Interaction Using Wrist-worn Passive Magneto-inductive Sensors". In: *Proceedings of the 2015 ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing.* ACM. 2015, pp. 15–26. DOI: 10.1145/2750858.2804271. URL: http://doi.org/10.1145/2750858.2804271.
- [14] Mariakakis, A., Sen, S., Lee, J., Kim, K.-H., "SAIL: Single Access Point-based Indoor Localization". In: *Proceedings of the 12th annual international conference on Mobile systems, applications, and services.* ACM. 2014, pp. 315–328. DOI: 10.1145/2594368.2594393. URL: http://doi.org/10.1145/2594368.2594393.

## **Conference Talks**

- [15] Drunk User Interfaces: Determining Blood Alcohol Level Through Everyday Smartphone Tasks. CHI. Montreal, QC, Apr. 2018.
- [16] BiliScreen: Smartphone-based Scleral Jaundice Monitoring for Liver and Pancreatic Disorders. Ubi-Comp. Maui, HI, Sept. 2017.
- [17] PupilScreen: Using Smartphones to Assess Traumatic Brain Injury. UbiComp. Maui, HI, Sept. 2017.
- [18] Ocular Symptom Detection Using Smartphones. UbiComp Doctoral School. Heidelberg, Germany, Sept. 2016.
- [19] SwitchBack: Improving Interaction with Mobile Devices. CHI. Seoul, South Korea, Apr. 2015.

#### **Guest Lectures**

- [20] "Diagnostic Smartphone Apps". CSE 599 N1: Modern Mobile Systems. Seattle, WA, Oct. 2018.
- [21] "Diagnostic Smartphone Apps". BIME 591: Research Colloquium. Seattle, WA, Nov. 2017.
- [22] "Ubiquitous Computing". CSE Direct Admits Seminar. Seattle, WA, Aug. 2017.
- [23] "Using Mobile Devices to Quantify Traditionally Qualitative Health Measures". HalfMoon Education: Internet of Things Workshop. Seattle, WA, Sept. 2017.
- [24] "Ubiquitous Computing". CSE Direct Admits Seminar. Seattle, WA, Aug. 2016.

#### **Invited Talks**

- [25] Objectifying Subjective Medical Assessments Using Smartphone Sensors. On-Site Interview at Georgia Tech. Atlanta, GA. Mar. 2019.
- [26] Objectifying Subjective Medical Assessments Using Smartphone Sensors. On-Site Interview at the University of Virginia. Charlottesville, VA. Feb. 2019.
- [27] BiliScreen: Smartphone-based Scleral Jaundice Monitoring for Liver and Pancreatic Disorders. mHealth Symposium at Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center. Seattle, WA. Nov. 2018.
- [28] BiliScreen: Smartphone-based Scleral Jaundice Monitoring for Liver and Pancreatic Disorders. Quantified Self Meetup. Seattle, WA. Nov. 2017.
- [29] BiliScreen: Smartphone-based Scleral Jaundice Monitoring for Liver and Pancreatic Disorders. UW CSE Industry Affiliates. Seattle, WA. Nov. 2017.

- [30] A Smartphone-based System for Assessing Intraocular Pressure. Microsoft Student Summit on Mobility, Systems, and Networking. Petaluma, CA. Feb. 2016.
- [31] Ocular Symptom Detection Using Smartphones. UW CSE Industry Affiliates. Seattle, WA. Oct. 2016.
- [32] SwitchBack: Improving Interaction with Mobile Devices. UW CSE Industry Affiliates. Seattle, WA. Oct. 2014.

## **Posters**

- [33] Mobile Sensing for Health and Public Safety. UW CSE Affiliates. Seattle, WA, Nov. 2018.
- [34] Mobile Sensing for Health and Public Safety. HCIC 2018. Pajaro Dunes, CA, June 2018.
- [35] A Smartphone-Based System for Assessing Intraocular Pressure + Non-invasive Approach. UW CSE Affiliates. Seattle, WA, Nov. 2017.
- [36] BiliScreen: Smartphone-Based Scleral Jaundice Monitoring for Liver and Pancreatic Disorders. UW CSE Affiliates. Seattle, WA, Nov. 2017.
- [37] A Smartphone-based System for Assessing Intraocular Pressure. EMBC 2016. Orlando FL, Aug. 2016.
- [38] Ocular Symptom Detection Using Smartphones. UW CSE Affiliates. Seattle, WA, Nov. 2016.
- [39] RePOV: Using Sensors and Vision to Facilitate Discoveries in Egocentric Videos. UW CSE Affiliates. Seattle, WA, Nov. 2015.
- [40] SwitchBack: Using Focus and Saccade Tracking to Guide Users' Attention for Mobile Task Resumption. UW CSE Affiliates. Seattle, WA, Nov. 2014.

#### **Patents**

- [41] McGrath, L., Law, A., Bly, R., Patel, S., Mariakakis, A., Baudin, J., "Smartphone-based Digital Pupillometer". U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 62/513,808. 2017.
- [42] Taylor, J., Patel, S., Mariakakis, A., "BiliCam for Adults". U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 62/513,825. 2017.
- [43] Mariakakis, A., Wang, E., Patel, S., Wen, J., "A Smartphone-based System for Assessing Intraocular Pressure". U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 62/289,755, 62/375,779. 2016.
- [44] Mariakakis, A., Srinivasan, V., Rachuri, K., Mukherji, A., "WatchUDrive: Differentiating Drivers and Passengers Using Smartwatches". 2016.
- [45] Mariakakis, A., Goel, M., Aumi, M. T. I., Patel, S. N., Wobbrock, J. O., "SwitchBack: Using Focus and Saccade Tracking to Guide Users' Attention for Mobile Task Resumption". U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 62/068,413. 2015.
- [46] Sen, S., Mariakakis, A., Lee, J.-G., "Localization Using Access Point". U.S. Patent 9883342B2. 2014. URL: https://patents.google.com/patent/US9883342B2.

## **Professional Service**

#### **Program Committee**

ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems, Late Breaking Work (CHI LBW) 2020 ACM User Interface Software and Technology (UIST) 2019 International Workshop on Ubiquitous Personal Assistance (UPA) 2018–2019
Reviewer (number of non-PC reviews)
Biomedical Optics Express
Outstanding reviews: CHI (1), UbiComp (5)
Organizing Committee
CHI Video Previews Co-Chair
Other
UbiComp Broadening Participation Workshop Mentor       2018         UbiComp Student Volunteer       2014         MobiSys Student Volunteer       2014

# **University Service**

NSF GRFP workshop coordinator	2016-2018
DUB graduate student coordinator	2017
Co-founder of DUB Doctoral Colloquium	2017
CSE graduate student coordinator	2016
CSE PhD application reader	2016

Active participant in the University of Washington's DawgBytes and Engineering Discovery Days programs for K-12 outreach

At least 50 lab tours and demos for a variety of visitors, including:

- Politicians (Senator Maria Cantwell)
- Military officials (General Kevin Chilton)
- Visiting faculty (Drs. Andy van Dam and Raj Reddy)
- National Center for Women & Information Technology (NCWIT)
- K-12 teachers
- Countless undergraduates and high schoolers

# **Industry Experience**

Sage Bionetworks Post-Doctoral Researcher (Seattle, WA)

Fall 2019—present

Mentor: Larsson Omberg To be disclosed later

Microsoft Research Research Intern (Redmond, WA)

Spring-Summer 2018

Mentors: Gonzalo Ramos, Asta Roseway

To be disclosed later

FX Palo Alto Laboratory Research Intern (Palo Alto, CA)

Summer 2015

Mentor: Daniel Avrahami

Developed interface that surfaces coincidences and similarities in egocentric video collections

Samsung Research America Research Intern (San Jose, CA)

Summer 2014

Mentors: Vijay Srinivasan, Kiran Rachuri, Evan Welbourne

Explored the application of inertial and image sensing in smartwatches for driving and eating detection

HP Labs Research Intern (Palo Alto, CA)

Summer 2013

Mentor: Souvik Sen

Developed indoor localization system that combines Wi-Fi ranging and inertial dead reckoning

Lutron Electronics Software Intern (Coopersburg, PA)

Summer 2010

Mentor: Ryan Bedell

Developed software for automatic PIR occupancy sensor tests and mass microcontroller programming

#### Selected Press

GeekWire: Geek of the Week: Duke grad Alex Mariakakis finds a home at UW and a vision for continued success

Paul G. Allen: 1 Year, 10 Innovations From UW's Paul G. Allen School That's Making the World a Better Place

Newsweek: This new app detects concussions just by looking into your eyes

BBC News: Selfie app "spots early signs of pancreatic cancer"

UW CSE News: 10th Anniversary of UW CSE's CS4HS

# **Teaching**

## University of Washington

EE PMP 590 A: Advanced Topics in Digital Computers . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Spring 2018 CSE 331: Software Design and Implementation (TA) . . . . Fall 2013, Winter 2013, Spring 2014

#### Online Courses

## **Duke University**

ECE 559: Advanced Digital System Design (TA) Spring 2013
ECE 54/280: Introduction to Signals and System (TA) Spring 2011, Spring 2012, Fall 2012
ECE 52: Introduction to Digital Systems (TA) Fall 2011
EGR 224: Electrical Fundamentals of Mechatronics (TA) Spring 2013
EGR 53/103: Computational Methods in Engineering (TA) Fall 2010, Fall 2011, Fall 2012

## Mentoring

Hung Ngo
Eric Chan
Megan Anne Banks (now at Oculus) Oct 2015–Jan 2018
Vardhman Mehta (now at Google)
Andy Li (now at Facebook) Jan 2015–June 2015
Thirdy Et (now at Facebook)
High School Research Advisees
High School Research Advisees